Rudolf Höber Papers 1886-1961 Mss.Ms.Coll.44
American Philosophical Society
Rudolf Höber Papers
1886-1961
Mss.Ms.Coll.44
American Philosophical Society
6.0 Linear feet
One of hundreds of German scholars displaced by the Nazis after 1933, Rudolf Höber was an early proponent of applying physicochemical methods to the analysis of the physiology of cell membranes, particularly their role in the regulation of transport, permeability, and electrical properties. For many years his Physikalische Chemie der Zelle und Gewebe (1902) and Lehrbuch der Physiologie des Menschen (1919) were the standard works in their field. The Höber Papers consist of five linear feet of family correspondence, with a small number of professional letters scattered throughout. Although Höber's physiological research, per se, is seldom discussed, the letters provide insight into the family life and privileged social milieu of a member of the German intellectual elite in the years prior to and immediately after the First World War, his loss of position after the rise to power of the Nazis, and the conditions of his emigration to the United States, his adjustment to American life, and his attempts to bring the remainder of his family to safety during the late 1930s. The collection is arranged in two series, Correspondence (Series I, 5.5 lin. feet), which is arranged chronologically, and Publications and miscellaneous (Series II, 0.5 lin. feet), which is arranged alphabetically.
Höber, Rudolf, b. 1873
Bibliography
Related Archival Materials note
The Printed Materials Department has copies of two editions of Höber's major works:
Höber, Rudolf, Lehrbuch der Physiologie des Menschen, 8th ed. (Bern, Switzerland, 1938).
Höber, Rudolf, Physikalische Chemie der Zellen und Gewebe (Bern, Switzerland, 1947).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of the Elfriede Fischer Hoeber, 1985.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of the German physiologist Rudolf Höber consist of five linear feet of family correspondence, with a small number of professional letters scattered throughout. Although Höber's physiological research, per se, is seldom discussed, the letters provide insight into the family life and privileged social milieu of a member of the German intellectual elite in the years prior to and immediately after the First World War, his loss of position after the rise to power of the Nazis, and the conditions of his emigration to the United States, his adjustment to American life, and his attempts to bring the remainder of his family to safety during the late 1930s. The collection is arranged in two series, Correspondence (Series I, 5.5 lin. feet), which is arranged chronologically, and Publications and miscellaneous (Series II, 0.5 lin. feet), which is arranged alphabetically.
After 1901, nearly all of the correspondence is between Höber and his wife, Josephine, with the exception being about 25 letters regarding Höber's academic positions in England and the United States after 1933, and a series of letters written by Höber to his children in Germany before 1938. The thickest documentation falls in the period 1898-1905, when Höber is in Zurich, and in the years after his emigration to the United States, while his children remained in Germany, 1935-1938. As might be expected, in this latter correspondence the Höbers are very circumspect when writing about conditions under the Nazis, at least as long as relatives remained in Germany, and they appear to have used a private code to refer to emigration or to express their views on the regime. There is little to document Höber's expulsion from Kiel in 1933.
Series II includes an interesting set of memoranda and some correspondence received by Höber while serving as Rektor of the University of Kiel, 1930-1931, as well as copies of a few his publications, some biographical materials, and an academic sash of unidentified origin. All but a few of the items in the collection are written in German, with the handwritten ones (the majority) written in the old script.
In their personal letters, all of the Höber's routinely referred to themselves and each other by affectionate nicknames, some more obscure than others. A list of these is included in the file marked "Biographical material" (Series II). This same list includes a list of code words used by the Höber's in correspondence between the United States and Germany during the Nazi period, 1933-1939. After their emigration to America, the Höbers have spelled their name Hoeber or Hober, depending on which branch of the family.
Biographical/Historical note
One of hundreds of German scholars displaced by the Nazis after 1933, Rudolf Höber was an early proponent of applying physicochemical methods to the analysis of the physiology of cell membranes, particularly their permeability and electric properties. Born into an intellectual family in Stettin, Germany (now Poland), on December 27, 1879, Höber studied at the Universities of Freiburg and Berlin before completing a medical degree at Erlangen in 1898. His dissertation was an experimental study of wound shock, Ueber experimentellen Shock durch Reizung der serösen Häute (Leipzig, 1897), yet even while he was writing it, he found himself drawn to the prospect of applying physical chemical methods to the analysis of living cells. From the time of his first academic appointment at the Physiological Institute of the University of Zurich (1897-1909), Höber therefore directed himself to an innovative course of physiological research.
As early as his first years at Zurich, Höber characterized his research interests as centering on a single question: "Was ist und was leistet die Zellmembran?" (What is the cell membrane and how does it function?). This simple question led him to a suite of pioneering studies on the fundamental physiological properties of the cell membrane, its role in the regulation of transport, permeability, and electrical properties. His Physikalische Chemie der Zelle und Gewebe (1902) was a landmark and helped cement Höber's growing reputation in the field. One of the first monographs on the subject, it was considered the standard text in cell physiology for two decades, passing through at least seven editions before 1926. Höber also published important works on intestinal resorption, the hydroxyl ion concentration of blood, the mechanism of narcosis and its influence upon permeability, and the physiological significance of colloids.
Höber was assisted in his research by his wife, Josephine Marx (1876-1941), whom he married in 1901. Josephine completed her own medical degree shortly after their marriage, becoming one of the first female physicians in Germany. The two often collaborated, even as Josephine maintained her own medical practice. They had three children, Johannes (1904-1977), Gabriele (1906-1988), and Ursula.
In 1909, Höber left Zurich for the prestigious Institute of Physiology at the University of Kiel, receiving a promotion to Ordinarius fuer Physiologie in 1912, and later becoming Director of the Institute (1915), Dean of the Medical School (twice), and eventually Rektor. At Kiel, his reputation continued to expand on the strength of his 1919 textbook Lehrbuch der Physiologie des Menschen (1919), which was as influential as Physikalische Chemie, passing through eight editions and translations into several foreign languages. His laboratory became a magnet for students from as far away as the United States and Japan and was much in demand as a lecturer throughout Europe, paying his first visit to the United States in 1929, when he attended the XIII International Congress of Physiological Sciences held at Woods Hole as president of the German Physiological Society. He and his colleagues, Albrecht Bethe and Emil Abderhalden were co-editors of essential journal Pflügers Archiv from 1918-1934.
Yet even an international reputation in his field did not insulate Höber when his country veered toward Fascism. Although neither a politician nor an activist, he earned the enmity of the Nazis when he sat on a University disciplinary court in 1931 that convicted and expelled six pro-Nazi students for their assault on a Lutheran clergyman. Within a week of Hitler seizing power in 1933, Höber himself became a target when his laboratory was taken over and he was confined to the second floor of his institute. Although he was briefly allowed to resume lecturing during the summer semester, by September he was forced into retirement by the Education Ministry of the state of Schleswig-Holstein.
The shocking turn of events made Höber into a minor cause celebre, and with the assistance of the physiologist A. V. Hill and the Rockefeller Foundation, he soon received an invitation to join the staff at the University College, London. In the following spring, 1934, with the support of Henry C. Bazett Höber was offered a position as visiting professor at the University of Pennsylvania. For several years, Höber subsisted on grant money from the Rockefeller Foundation, the Emergency Committee in Aid of Displaced German Scholars, the United Jewish Appeal, and the American Philosophical Society. He was able to bring his wife and daughter Ursula with him in 1934, and over the next three years he brought his children Johannes and Gabriele and their families. As she had in Germany, Josephine worked with Höber in his laboratory. When Höber died in Philadelphia in 1953, he was eulogized as a "pioneer and co-founder of a new direction in physiology" as well as a caring mentor. Despite the turmoil and dislocations of his life, Höber's bibliography surpassed 100 articles.
Höber, Gabriele, 1906-1988; Höber, Johannes U., 1904-1977; Höber, Josephine Marx, 1876-1941; Höber, Ursula, 1912-1990; Universität Kiel; Cell physiologists--Germany; German-Americans--Pennsylvania; Germany--History--1919-1933; Physiologists--Germany; Political refugees--Germany
- Series I. Correspondence, 1890-1961; 1 folder
  - Correspondence, 1890 July; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1895 August; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1896 March; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1896 April; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1896 May; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1896 June; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1896 July; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1896 August; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1896 September; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1896 October; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1896 November; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1896 December; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, ca.1896; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, ca.1896-1901; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1897 January; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1897 February; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1897 March; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1897 April; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1897 May; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1897 June; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1897 July; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1897 August; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1897 September; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1897 October; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1897 November; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1897 December; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898 January; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898 February; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898 March; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898 April; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898 May; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898 June; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898 July; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898 August; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898 September; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898 October; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898 November; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898 December; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1899 January; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1899 February; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1899 March; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1899 April; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1899 May; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1899 June; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1899 July; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1899 August; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1899 September; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1899 October; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1899 November; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1899 December; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, ca.1899; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1900 January; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1900 February; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1900 March; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1900 April; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1900 May; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1900 June; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1900 July; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1900 August; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1900 September; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1900 October; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1900 November; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1900 December; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, ca.1900; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1901 January; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1901 February; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1901 March; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1901 April; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1901 May; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1901 June; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1901 July; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1901 August; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1901 September; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1901 October; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1901 November; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1901 December; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, ca.1901; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1902 January; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1902 February; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1902 March; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1902 April; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1902 December; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1903 March; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1903 April; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1903 May; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1903 August; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1903 October; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1903 November; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1903 December; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1904 January; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1904 February; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1904 March; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1904 April; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1904 May; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1904 June; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1904 July; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1904 September; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1905 May; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1905 September; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1905 October; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1905 November; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1905 December; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, ca.1905; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1906 January; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1906 February; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1906 March; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1906 April; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1906 May; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1906 June; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1906 July; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1906 August; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1906 September; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1906 October; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, ca.1906; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1909 January; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1909 March; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1909 April; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1909 June; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1909 October; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1909 December; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1910 February; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1910 March; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1910 July; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1910 August; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1910 September; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1910 October; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1910 December; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, ca.1910; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1911 January; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1911 July; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1911 September; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1911 December; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1912 March; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1912 April; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1912 July; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1912 August; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1912 September; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1912 October; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1912 December; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1913 March; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1913 May; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1913 June; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1913 August; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1913 September; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1913 November; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1914 April; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1914 June; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1914 August; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1915 September; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1916 February; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1916 March; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1916 October; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1917 April; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1917 July; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1917 August; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1918 January; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1918 April; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1918 June; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1918 October; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1919 July; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1920 February; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1920 May; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1920 July; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1921 April; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1921 August; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1921 October; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1922 April; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1924 October; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1925 October; 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1926 March; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1926 April; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1926 May; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1926 July; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1926 October; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, ca.1926; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1927 May; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1927 October; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, ca.1927; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1928 February; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1929 August; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1929 September; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1929 October; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1930 July; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1930 August; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1930 September; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1930 October; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, ca.1930; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1931 February; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1933 July; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1933 November; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1933 December; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1934 January; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1934 February; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1934 March; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1934 April; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1934 May; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1934 June; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1934 July; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1934 August; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1934 September; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1934 October; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1934 November; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1934 December; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, ca.1934; 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1935 January; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1935 February; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1935 March; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1935 April; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1935 May; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1935 June; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1935 July; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1935 August; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1935 September; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1935 October; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1935 November; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1935 December; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, ca.1935; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1936 January; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1936 February; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1936 March; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1936 April; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1936 May; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1936 June; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1936 July; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1936 August; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1936 September; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1936 October; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1936 November; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1936 December; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, ca.1936; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1937 January; 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1937 February; 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1937 March; 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1937 April; 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1937 May; 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1937 June; 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1937 July; 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1937 August; 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1937 September; 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1937 October; 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1937 November; 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1937 December; 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, ca.1937; 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with children in Germany, 1938 January-June; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1938 January; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1938 February; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1938 March; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1938 April; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1938 May; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1938 June; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1938 July; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1938 August; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1938 September; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1938 October; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1938 November; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1938 December; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, ca.1938; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1939 January; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1939 June; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1939 July; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1939 August; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1939 November; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1939 December; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1940 April; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1940 June; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1940 July; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1940 August; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1961; 1 folder (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1 folder (Box 11)
- Series II. Publications and Miscellaneous, 1886-; 1 folder (Box 12)
  - Catalogue, 1950/51; 1 item; Christian-Albrechts-Universität (Box 12)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes mention of Physiological Laboratory, now named after Höber.
  - Engraving, n.d.; 1 item (Box 12)
  - "Untersuchungen über den der Sekretionsarbeit zugrunde liegenden Stoffwechsel von Leber, Niere und Speicheldruüse", 1931; 1 item; Ferrari, Rodolfo; Höber, Rudolf, b. 1873 (Box 12)
    Pflügers Archiv für die gesamte Physiologie 232 (1933): 299-321.